Register of the O. Edmund Clubb Papers, 1940-1988
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1940-1983.
  - "Soviet Political Strategy in Asia," World Today, 1956 May (attributed to "A. B. C."). Correspondence, two typescript drafts, and printed copy (17)
  - "Crazy-Quilt 'Foreign Aid'," The Nation, 1956 May 9. Typescript (Folder 18)
  - Review of Chinese documents project (part two), submitted to Far Eastern Quarterly, 1956 July 15. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 19)
  - Review of Henry Wei, China and Soviet Russia, submitted to Far Eastern Survey, 1956 August 6. Correspondence and typescript (20)
  - "Chiang Kai-Shek's Waterloo: The Battle of the Hwai-Hai," Pacific Historical Review, 1956 November. Correspondence, two typescript drafts, and printed copy (Folder 21)
  - "The Cold War and the Campaign," The Progressive, 1956 November. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 22)
  - Review of Tieh-tseng Li, The Historical Status of Tibet, published in The Annals of the American Academy of Political Science, 1956 November. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 23)
  - "Tibet's Strategic Position," Eastern World, 1956 December. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 24)
  - Books reviews submitted to The Nation, 1957. Correspondence and typescript (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - Editorials submitted to The Nation, 1957. Correspondence and three typescript texts (Folder 2)
  - "Challenge to the West," The Progressive, 1957 January. Printed copy (Folder 3)
  - "The Ramparts We Rent," The Nation, 1957 January 26. Correspondence, typescript, galley proof, and printed copy (Folder 4)
  - "Pivot of History," Military Review, 1957 February. Correspondence only (Folder 5)
  - "Arms Diplomacy in the Atlantic," article submitted to The Nation (not published), 1957 March 24. Correspondence and three typescript drafts (Folder 6)
  - "Asia's Revolution Moves Westward," The Progressive, 1957 May. Typescript draft and corrections (Folder 7)
  - "Crisis in Our Coalition," Frontier, 1957 June. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Formosa: The Dream Dissolves," The Nation, 1957 June 8. Typescript and printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "Suez and the Indian Ocean," U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 1957 August. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Manchuria - Communist Keystone," Military Review, 1957 November. Correspondence, two typescript drafts, and printed copy (Folder 11)
  - "Manchuria in the Balance, 1945-1946," Pacific Historical Review, 1957 November. Correspondence, three typescript drafts, printed copy, and typescript reply (not pulbished) to a critic of the original article (Folder 12)
  - "America, Russia, and the Chinese Revolution," 1958. Correspondence and outline only (Folder 13)
  - Editorials submitted to The Nation, 1958. Correspondence and three typescript texts (Folder 14)
  - "The Ordeal of the West," unpublished article, 1958. Correspondence and three typescript drafts (Folder 15)
  - "Military Debacle in Manchuria," The Army Quarterly and Defence Journal (London), 1958 January. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 16)
  - "The Foreign Policy Issue - Survival," article submitted to The Nation (unpublished), 1958 March. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 17)
  - "The Role of Turkestan in Soviet Middle East Policy," World Today, 1958 May. Correspondence, typescript, galley proof, and printed copy (Folder 18)
  - "Turkestan in Transition," Eastern World, 1958 August. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 19)
  - "Chiang's Shadow Over Warsaw," The Reporter, 1958 October 2. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 20)
  - "Our China Policy Reaches Dead End," The Progressive, 1958 November. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 21)
  - "Soviet Oriental Studies and the Asian Revolution," Pacific Affairs, 1958 December. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 22)
  - "Northward the Course of Empire," Military Review, 1959 January. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 23)
  - "Needed - The Discovery of Asia," article submitted to The American Scholar (not published), 1959 February. Correspondence and three typescript drafts (Folder 24)
  - Editorial submitted to The Nation, 1959 April 30. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 25)
  - "Sino-Soviet Power in the West Pacific," U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 1959 June. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 26)
  - "Our Ignorance of Asia," The Progressive, 1959 July. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 27)
  - "The Old Order Passes in Tibet," Eastern World, 1959 August. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 28)
  - "Formosa's Future," Frontier, 1959 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - "Oriental Studies Through Soviet Eyes," Pacific Affairs, 1959 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "China's Drive Toward Empire," The Progressive, 1959 October. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Formosa and the Offshore Islands in American Policy, 1950-1955," Political Science Quarterly, 1959 December. Correspondence, typescript, printed copy, and reprint (Folder 4)
  - Book reviews submitted to Far Eastern Survey, 1960. Correspondence and four typescript texts (Folder 5)
  - "Tibet and India," talk on radio station WKCR, 1960 January 6. Memorandum and typescript (Folder 6)
  - "On the Roof of the World," Military Review, 1960 February. Correspondence, clipping, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 7)
  - Editorial submitted to The Nation, 1960 June 23. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Review of Allen S. Whiting, China Crosses the Yalu, The Journal of Asian Studies, 1961 January 18. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "The Lesson of Laos," The Progressive, 1961 May. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Soviet versus Chinese Communism," Military Review, 1961 November. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 11)
  - Letters to the editor, The New York Times, 1962-1984. Correspondence and printed copies (Folder 12)
  - "New Stage in Sino-American Relations," article submitted to The Progressive (not published), 1962 January 18. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 13)
  - "Trap in Vietnam," The Progressive, 1962 April. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - "Patchwork on the Sino-Soviet Alliance," Military Review, 1962 August. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 15)
  - Did U.S. Play into Communist Hands in Asia?" The National Observer, 1962 October 15. Printed copy (Folder 16)
  - "The Sino-Indian Border Conflict," 1962 November 7. Typescript (Folder 17)
  - "China's Position in Asia," Journal of International Affairs, 1963 Spring. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 18)
  - "The 1958 Formosa Strait Crisis in Sino-American Relations," article submitted to The China Quarterly (not published), 1963 August 9. Correspondence and two typescript texts (Folder 19)
  - "Parting of the Ways," Military Review, 1963 October. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 20)
  - "Toward an Affirmative Approach to China," The Progressive, 1963 November. Correspondence and three typescript texts (Folder 21)
  - "The International Position of Communist China," paper delivered at the Hammarskjöld Forums, New York, 1963 December 2. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 22)
  - 20th Century China, 1964. Typescript
  - Chapters 1-6 (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - Chapters 7-12 (Folder 2)
  - "Living with China as a Great Power," The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1964 January. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 3)
  - "Asia: Factors, Issues, and Propositions," internal memorandum prepared for Americans for Democratic Action, 1964 January 23. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "China's Borders in History, Law, and Politics," seminar paper, Columbia University, 1964 April. Printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "Sino-Soviet Frontier," Military Review, 1964 July. Correspondence and two typescript texts (Folder 6)
  - "Communist China's Foreign Affairs," speech, U.S. Army Signal Center, Fort Monmouth, New Jersey, 1964 October 13. Correspondence and clipping (Folder 7)
  - Speech, East Asian Institute, Columbia University, 1964 November. Clipping (Folder 8)
  - "Nuclear Disarmament and Mainland China," policy paper prepared for Americans for Democratic Action, 1964 November 18. Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "The New World Triangle," The Progressive, 1964 December. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Vietnam and the End of the SEATO Decade," The Correspondent, 1965 Winter. Correspondence (Folder 11)
  - "Sino-American Relations and the Future of Formosa," Political Science Quarterly, 1965 March. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 12)
  - Speech, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, New York, 1965 March 19. Correspondence, press release, and clipping (Folder 13)
  - "The World that Is China," address, National Alumni Program of Columbia University, 1965 March 24. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - Speech, Columbia University, 1965 March 25. Announcement and clipping (Folder 15)
  - "The United States and Asia," article submitted to The Progressive (not published), 1965 March 25. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 16)
  - Interview, RKO-General Broadcasting, 1965 April 5. Correspondence and transcript (Folder 17)
  - "Our China Policy," Christianity and Crisis, 1965 April 19. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 18)
  - "The Second World Revolution," The Progressive, 1965 June. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 19)
  - "China: Confucius and the Commissars," chapter in The Nature of the Non-Western World, 1965 July 28. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 20)
  - "How China Was 'Lost'," book review submitted to The New York Herald Tribune, 1965 August 11. Typescript (Folder 21)
  - "Red China," Marine Corps Gazette, 1965 October. Correspondence (Folder 22)
  - "China: A Stranger and Afraid," Columbia University Forum, 1966 Winter. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 23)
  - China's View of the United States," article submitted to the Associated Press (not published), 1966 January 31. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 24)
  - "The Cost of Vietnam," The Progressive, 1966 April. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 25)
  - "Sino-American Relations," Diplomat, 1966 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy Biographical Dictionary of Republican China, (Howard Boorman, editor), 1967-1969 (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and memoranda (Folder 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 3)
  - Typescript (Folder 4-7)
  - "Is Mao's Rule Nearing End?" article written for United Press International, 1967 January 14. Correspondence and printed copy (Box 17., Folder 1)
  - "Behind the Cultural Revolution," War/Peace Report, 1967 March. Correspondence and printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "Russia's Entry into the 'Unequal Treaty System'," seminar paper, Columbia University, 1967 March 29. Printed copy (Folder 3)
  - Communism in China, 1968. Correspondence, typescript and printed copy of preface, and maps (Folder 4)
  - "The Challenge of Communist China," speech to Columbia University Club of Houston, 1968 March 14. Program and typescript (Folder 5)
  - "A Hard Look at China," interview, World Campus, 1968 April. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "China and the Western World," Current History, 1968 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 7)
  - Review of Alberto Moravia, The Red Book and the Great Wall, Saturday Review, 1968 November 9. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Putting China into Perspective," review of books on China, War/Peace Report, 1969 April. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "McCarthyism and Our Asian Policy," Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars, 1969 May. Two typescript texts (Folder 10)
  - "Chinese Communist Ideology in Revolution," lecture, McMaster University, 1969 October 24. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - "Inside the White Paper - from the Outside," speech, American Historical Association, 1969 December 29. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - China's Borderlands, projected book (not published), 1970(?). Correspondence and typescript (Folder 13)
  - "The Unsolved 'China Question'," review of books on China, 1970(?). Typescript (Folder 14)
  - "The Global Triangle," The Progressive, 1970 March. Printed copy (15)
  - "Our Asia Policy: The House Cold Warriors Built," article submitted to The New York Review of Books (not published), 1970 May 2. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 16)
  - "China and the United States: Collision Course?" Current History, 1970 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "It's a New War," The Progressive, 1970 October. Printed copy (Folder 18)
  - Review of Andrew Hacker, The End of the American Era, The Nation, 1970 September 7. Printed copy (Folder 19)
  - China and Russia: The 'Great Game', 1971. Typescript (20-21)
  - Book reviews, Saturday Review, 1971. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copies (Folder 22)
  - "State of Our Asia Policy," The New York Times, 1971 March 1. Correspondence and typescript (Box 18., Folder 1)
  - Review of John Robinson Beal, Marshall in China, submitted to The American Political Science Review, 1971 March 6. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 2)
  - Review of books on China, submitted to Canadian Slavic Studies, 1971 March 14. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 3)
  - Review of books on China, submitted to The Saturday Review, 1971 May 10. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 4)
  - Review of Neville Maxwell, India's China War, submitted to Political Science Quarterly, 1971 May 14. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 5)
  - "China's Plans: An Informed Guess," The Nation, 1971 May 17. Printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Games Cold Warriors Play," The New York Times, 1971 July 26. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 7)
  - "China's Strategic Shift," The Progressive, 1971 August. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "China and the United States: Beyond Pingpong," Current History, 1971 September. Correspondence, typescript, and galley proof (Folder 9)
  - "Chinese Dreamer of Dreams," article submitted to The New York Times, 1972 February 17. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 10)
  - "China Since 1949: Seeking the Road to National Greatness," The New York Times, 1972 February 23. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 11)
  - "A New China, the Old Politics," Worldview, 1972 March. Printed copy (Folder 12)
  - "The President's Prospects in Moscow," The New York Times, 1972 May 23. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 13)
  - "China, Russia, and East Asia," Pacific Commentary, 1972 July. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 14)
  - "Negotiating the Future of Taiwan," Worldview, 1972 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 15)
  - "Sino-Soviet Relations and the Economic Imperative," Current History, 1972 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 16)
  - Review of Foster Rhea Dulles, American Policy Toward Communist China 1949-1969, submitted to The Virginia Quarterly Review, 1972 October 14. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 17)
  - "Our Indochina War," Current History, 1972 December. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 18)
  - "Vietnam: A Lesson from History," The New York Times, 1972 December 5. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 19)
  - Article for Collier's Encyclopedia, 1973. Correspondence (Folder 20)
  - "The Cease-Fire," The Nation,1973 February 12. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 21)
  - "Massive Changes Are in Course in Asia," The New York Times, 1973 February 25. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 22)
  - "China: Looking to the Future," paper delivered at 26th National Roosevelt Day of Americans for Democratic Action, 1973 March 1. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 23)
  - "Indochina and U.S. Aid," Worldview, 1973 May. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 24)
  - "New Horizons in U.S.-Soviet Trade," The Progressive, 1973 June. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 25)
  - "Security Risks: National Security and the State Department," Worldview, 1973 August. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 26)
  - "Maoism versus Khruschevism: Ten Years," The Nation, 1973 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 27)
  - The Witness and I, 1974
  - Notes (Box 19., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Folder 2)
  - Typescript (Folder 3-4)
  - Printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "Power in the World Economic Arena," The New York Times, 1974 June 29. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 6)
  - "America Alone," The Progressive, 1974 August. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 7)
  - "China and the Superpowers," Current History, 1974 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "The Soviet Union in World Trade," Worldview, 1974 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "Witchhunting and American Foreign Relations," remarks delivered at a reception for The Nation, 1974 November 15. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 10)
  - "On All the Evidence," Foreign Service Journal, 1974 December. Printed copy (Folder 11)
  - Review of Ross Koen, The China Lobby in American Politics, The Progressive, 1975 January. Correspondence and typescript (Box 20., Folder 1)
  - "'Project Interpendence' vs. Economic Nationalism," article submitted to The New York Times (not published), 1975 January 28. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 2)
  - "China and the Big 2," The New York Times, 1975 February 3. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 3)
  - "Third World Trade: USSR vs. China," Worldview, 1975 April. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 4)
  - "Soviet-American Trade: Can't We Do Anything Right?" The Nation, 1975 April 26. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "Latin America in Revolt," article submitted to The New York Times (not published), 1975 June 6. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 6)
  - "The Third World vs.'Superpower'," Worldview, 1975 July-August. Printed copy (Folder 7)
  - "The New Power Imbalance in Southeast Asia," Current History, 1975 December. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Saying, 'National Security...'," article, 1976(?). Typescript (Folder 9)
  - "China and the U.S. After Chou," The Nation, 1976 January 31. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "'Intelligence,' Diplomacy, and a New World Order," article submitted to The New York Times (not published). Correspondence and typescript (Folder 11)
  - "The Hemisphere Falls Apart," The Progressive, 1976 March. Correspondence and two typescript texts (Folder 12)
  - "China Looks Beyond Mao: The 'Struggle Between Two Lines'," The Nation, 1976 May 1. Correspondence and printed copy (Folder 13)
  - Review of C. L. Sulzberger, The Coldest War, Slavic Review, 1976 July. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 14)
  - "China and the West Pacific Powers," Current History, 1976 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 15)
  - "Revolution or 'Revisionism'," The Nation, 1976 September. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 16)
  - "What the 'Pacific Doctrine' Overlooks," Worldview, 1976 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "China's Options After Mao," editorial, The Nation, 1976 September 25. Printed copy (Folder 18)
  - Remarks on China to The American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia, 1976 November 12. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 19)
  - "China's Grand Strategy," article submitted to Foreign Affairs (not published), 1977 February. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 20)
  - "'Coexistence' After Mao," The Progressive, 1977 February. Correspondence and printed copy (Folder 21)
  - "China After Mao," Current History, 1977 September. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 22)
  - "Morality, Law, and the New World Order," Worldview, 1977 September. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 23)
  - "China's 'Revolutionary' Grand Strategy," article submitted to Foreign Policy (not published), 1978. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 24)
  - Radio commentaries for "In the Public Interest" (not broadcast), 1978. Correspondence and four typescript texts (Box 21., Folder 1)
  - "China's New Constitution: 'Great Order' Under Hua Kuo-feng," The Nation, 1978 April 8. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "China and the Three Worlds," Current History, 1978 September. Two typescript texts and printed copy (Folder 3)
  - Article on China, 1979 January 17. Typescript (Folder 4)
  - "China and America," The New York Times Magazine, 1979 January 28. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 5)
  - "Chinese Checkmate: The Taiwan Question," The Nation, 1979 February 24. Correspondence, typescript, galley proof, and printed copy (Folder 6)
  - "Foreign Policy Disasters - Why?" article submitted to The New York Times, 1979 March 19. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 7)
  - "Blunder in Vietnam: China Drops a Stone on Its Own Foot," The Nation, 1979 March 24. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "China and the West Pacific Powers," lecture, Syracuse University, 1979 Summer. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - "The Perils of a Political Foreign Policy," The Nation, 1979 December 8. Correspondence, two typescript texts, and printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Peking's Courtship of 'the West' Beyond SALT," Just for the Press, 1980 January-February. Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy (Folder 11)
  - Review of Gary May, China Scapegoat: The Diplomatic Ordeal of John Carter Vincent, Worldview, 1980 January-February. Printed copy (Folder 12)
  - "The Carter Doctrine and the Ayatollah Khomeini," article submitted to The New York Times, 1980 February 22. Correspondence and two typescript texts (Folder 13)
  - "The Middle East: Superpowers Keep Out," The Nation, 1980 May 31. Printed copy (Folder 14)
  - "China and the 'Industrialized Democracies'," Current History, 1980 September. Printed copy (Folder 15)
  - "The Diminution of Diplomatic Expertise," article submitted to Worldview (not published), 1980 October 16. Correspondence and two typescript texts (Folder 16)
  - "De-Maoizing China: A Revolution on Trial," The Nation, 1981 January 31. Printed copy (Box 22., Folder 1)
  - "America's China Policy," Current History, 1981 September. Printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "Planning for War - And for Peace," unpublished article, 1983 April 4. Correspondence and typescript (Folder 3)
  - "The Martial Syndrome in the Nuclear Age," article submitted to The Nation (not published), 1983 December 15. Correspondence and three typescript texts (Folder 4)
- ACADEMIC FILE, 1959-1965.
  Correspondence, lecture outlines, and memoranda, relating to Clubb's academic career
  - Brooklyn College (Box 22., Folder 5)
  - Columbia University (Folder 6-7)
- MARIANN CLUBB FILE, 1946-1982
  - Autobiography, n.d. Holograph and typescript (Box 22., Folder 8)
  - Autobiography (Box 23., Folder 1-3)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1982 (Folder 4)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1956-1983.
  Correspondence, memoranda, and printed matter
  - American Committee on East-West Accord (Box 23., Folder 5)
  - Americans for Democratic Action (Folder 6)
  - Asia Scholars to End the War (Folder 7)
  - China - Politics and government (Box 24., Folder 1-2)
  - Committee for New China Policy (Folder 3)
  - Democratic National Committee (Folder 4-5)
  - Democratic National Committee (Box 25., Folder 1)